<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
  <channel>
    <title> - Articles</title>
    <description>Scribbles &amp; Images</description>
    <link>
    http://localhost:5000</link>
    
      
      <item>
        <title>North Kalimantan</title>
        
          <description>&lt;p&gt;It was time to go north. As much as I enjoyed my time in Kalimantan Timur, the Eastern part of the island, it was time to move on. Locals from whence I came warned there really weren’t a lot of things going on in the North. Spending a week there, those claims aren’t entirely unfounded. At least seen from a tourist’s pair of eyes.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I’d made contact with a woman up there, willing to meet and help out during my stay there. She was a history teacher, living in Malinau and working in Setulang village, three-quarters ride away. The pay was substantially better out in the districts. She conceded though, that it was tough to be working out here on her own and that it had taken a toll on her emotionally, but claimed that for her, it was a better choice. It allowed her save up and go on her own travels one day.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Back in Malinau, I was trying to understand better where the hell I had brought myself. While true that there was a whole lot of nothing in this town, there were discoveries and observations to be made. A bunch of missionaries was in my hotel. Christian, white ones. They loved being there. Every moment. To their mind, doing imporant work. God’s work, in fact. Preaching to people the existence of the legendary and imaginary character sending people to heaven or hell. Whenever I lay eyes on religious structures, it pause me to think. I can never figure out what function these structures serve. Not really.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This church in Setulang village came with high-caliber megaphones announcing Sunday services.
What’s their mission, their purpose and what good are they bringing into the world of 2018? I mean, surely, in their eyes, they’re doing great, indoctrinating others to their particular beliefs, but they still divide the world, into us and them How about preaching something that unify us all? Of course that’s not happening. People don’t simply abandon their beliefs, do they? Especially if they make good, profitable lives on them. Especially if it’s their culture.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Later, I’m sitting in a restaurant. Next to me, a table of 3, discussing something. They’re curious to have a white face in their midst and I’m invited over. One of them has thorougly mastered the English language. They’re discussing mining business. He has literally struck gold. Geologists discovered gold on his land. Now he’s working on setting up operations and securing finances, but it needs to be carried out in secrecy. Mining is political in Kalimantan, as that’s where much power lays and the extension therof, money. All sorts of shady things happen to make political statements in that regard. He gives examples that political entities go so far as to sabotage mining operations causing them to leak chemicals into the rivers. Chemicals killing marine life downstream and being drank by people. This, to create problems for the operators who somehow were cooperating with the wrong side.
He dicusses Bruno Manser, the incredible Swizz environmentalist who mysteriously disappears disrespecting the Borneo elite. In his view, killed. Furhter making references to The Borneo Case, a documentary featuring the insidious nature of what happened in Borneo and where the money went.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In this part of the world, you’re free to do what you want. Rape, pillage and the uprooting of humans, their communities and culture is perfectly legitimate by its rulers, so long as you pay them. Stories most of us will not know. Even if we did, it wouldn’t have mattered. Noone knows these people, noone hears their screams as everything is taken away from them. Destruction on unbelievable scales. Once an island of rain forest, now one of plantations. Of people and communities and cultures, shattered, run over, to be forever gone. Grotesqueness of which can not be phantomed.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Back in Malinau, I’d been invited to attend an event that consisted of a van full of books and children reading from them. The absence of a library, had prompted community members to come up with this initiative in an attempt to inspire and provide young people the opportunity to become familiar with books. They even asked me to do an interview.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
        
        <pubDate>Mon, 20 Aug 2018 00:00:00 +0700</pubDate>
        <link>
        http://localhost:5000/north-kalimantan</link>
        <guid isPermaLink="true">http://localhost:5000/north-kalimantan</guid>
      </item>
      
    
      
      <item>
        <title>Backpacking Kalimantan Independently</title>
        
          <description>&lt;p&gt;A trip to the Malaysian side of Borneo in June, sparked an interest for this island of human and cultural diversity. Not long after, I was entering the Indonesian side of the island, named Kalimantan. Arriving Pontianak with an aim of backpacking the island in its entirety, I soon discovered that travel here is quite different from that of other destinations in South East Asia(SEA)&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;what-to-expect-from-kalimantan&quot;&gt;What to expect from Kalimantan&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Kalimantan is not a typical destination for the backpackers roaming the region. Perhaps for good reasons. The infrastructure having simplified travel in more traditional SEA destinations is yet to be developed here, and, as far as catering to English speaking travelers’ needs go, the industry has improvements to do. With the exception of a few official and independent tour agents’ websites, information in the English language is hard to come by. Add to that a people struggling with said language, with notable sights few and far between as well as of things to do, the poor road conditions, in addition to pollution and a scarcity of online accommodations. The list is long. It’s apparent why it’s not a mainstream destination. They have something else, though. They have people. Utterly great people who will take you on unforgettable adventures.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;As such, the island lends itself as a staging point for adventure travel and getting off the beaten path. A desire for novel experiences, to connect with people, their culture and place in the world should be primary reasons for wanting to come here. Kalimantan is also a looking glass into the environmental destruction the world faced in its quest for resources and profits. No doubt, you’re forging your own adventures in Kalimantan.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The island’s greatest asset is its friendly and hospitable people who unlike the Malaysian counterpart have not yet had much exposure to foreign travelers. As such Kalimantan serves as a place for meeting people of different backgrounds, some eager to learn about your world and teach you about theirs. Great place for cultural exchanges, in other words.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;how-to-backpack-kalimantan&quot;&gt;How to backpack Kalimantan&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;A lesser traveled destination, backpacking this island did require some adaptations in how I’d usually traveled the region. While stays in hostels are commonly the norm for backpackers in the region, this is less often an option for Kalimantan. Thus my options were staying at hotels serving mostly domestic business and tourist travelers, or, become flexible in my approach. By flexible,  I mean turning to Couchsurfing. Having tried both, the best experiences come from not only meeting the locals, but also staying with them.
For the uninitiated, the prospect of staying with Couchsurfers isa daunting one. In hindsight, however, the prospect of having backpacked Kalimantan without their aid would be even more so. True, it is exhausting to be immersed in a different culture, but if you want easy, you woulnd’t be coming here. An active and energetic Couchsurfing scene in Kalimantan is ready to take you in and show you what they’re about. I imagine that few who opts to couchsurf this island disagrees.
Indeed, the people more than made up for the lack of sights and activities typically found in more popular destinations. Go check it out.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
        
        <pubDate>Wed, 08 Aug 2018 00:00:00 +0700</pubDate>
        <link>
        http://localhost:5000/backpacking-kalimantan-timur-independently</link>
        <guid isPermaLink="true">http://localhost:5000/backpacking-kalimantan-timur-independently</guid>
      </item>
      
    
      
      <item>
        <title>ERAU Festival in Tenggarong 2018, Kalimantan Timur</title>
        
          <description>&lt;h2 id=&quot;visiting-the-erau-festival-in-tenggarong-kalimantan-timur&quot;&gt;Visiting the ERAU festival in Tenggarong, Kalimantan Timur&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I’d heard of a UNESCO endorsed festival coming up, in the eastern parts of Kalimantan and was on my way there to find out what it was about. Little information was available online, but I had been able to gather it was a week-long festival featuring folk costumes, music, and dances. A true cultural festival and a big one at it, if rumours were to be believed.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I had noticed through advertising on my flight to Kalimantan that Tenggarong was trying to establish itself as a tourist destination. Having arrived town, it was possible to see how. Although, they appeared to be targeting a domestic audience. A western traveler would probably have found the whole place a little underwhelming. I wasn’t there to be overwhelmed by grandiosity however, I was simply there to attend their festival and get a glimpse into the culture this festival could offer.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;During the performances, it was possible to gain an insight into the differing group’s culture. Particularly of interest to me, was how the Western performances compared to the Indonesian ones. A few European groups had ventured all the way to Tenggarong in an attempt to display their culture to the local audience. Even for an individual as uninformed in these matters, the contrasts between the two worlds were noticeable the. While I’m not one to elaborate on the differences, it seemed clear that these worlds were eons apart. Fascinating to say the least.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;As a paled skinned man in these parts, I was sure to draw a lot of attention. Undeservedly, it elevates my status in this society. I’m suddenly an elite member, and, as I’ve come to learn, that brings about certain additional privileges. Elite in this society happen to be those having positions in the government. Or, own a coal mine. During the entirety of the festival, members of the government were given priority seating and had an excellent vantage point on the festivities. The plebs however, were asked to sit elsewhere. Preferably far away. It was interesting to observe how blatant this separation between government and ordinary people was. I was at times appalled due my beliefs in equality. The pale skin gave similar advantages and when asked to join the VIP arena, I wasn’t about to say no. Quite selfish, I know, but what can I do? To change this phenomena? Besides, I wanted to shoot some pictures.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Tenggarong, along with Balikapan, was one of the prettier places I visited in Kalimantan. It was noticeable how they’ve been trying to carve out their own place in the world of tourism. It was impressive how the community had been working together to arrange a free festival for everybody to join, or,  as one of their slogans read; “creating something out of nothing”. Indeed they had created something out of nothing. Just next year, I hope they make this place a little more accessible through more information in the English language.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
        
        <pubDate>Wed, 25 Jul 2018 00:00:00 +0700</pubDate>
        <link>
        http://localhost:5000/erau-festival-tenggarong-kalimantan-timur</link>
        <guid isPermaLink="true">http://localhost:5000/erau-festival-tenggarong-kalimantan-timur</guid>
      </item>
      
    
      
      <item>
        <title>Backpacking Kalimantan</title>
        
          <description>&lt;p&gt;Returning to Balikpapan, I had already been here a few times in transit. This time with the intention of spending a couple of nights. As I found, this was a a rather backpacker friendly destination. Maybe not in the traditional sense where there’s a range of accommodations and activities. No, in the sense that there’s a strong couchsurfing community bent on giving you a great time by traveling with them.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;While not a spectacular city, it was of the prettier I saw whilst backpacking Kalimantan. It was almost as if they cared about their environment, at least more so than I noticed elsewhere. Pollution was less rampant, traffic less congested and even a cleaner smell. The architecture was a little more than the usual random patchwork of brick and concrete buildings erected as soon they could be afforded. Parts of the city could actually be accused of being charming, with a myriad of concept cafes and restos having come up in selected areas.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;##Crocodile zoo
A visit to the crocodile zoo, commonly encountered in South-East Asia, I avoid these places like the plague. This time I made an exception, for no other reason than wanting to see how bad it was. The minute I set foot in there, I has my answer. Not only was it bad. It was worse than my already low expectations. Since we had already ridden out there, I first accept the discriminatory foreigner price being charged on me. Verily, it would have been more joyful to watch my money burn than swallow the anger that arose from being charged the different price, merely based on my complexity. Sadly, now, a common phenomena in these neighborhoods.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;But the exception is made. Just this one time. Just to see how crap it really is, to be done and get it over with. I couldn’t possibly imagine there being a market for these attractions, however there is. A farm with crocs. Hundreds of them. Maybe farm is not the right way to put it. It was more like crappy crocodile village. Some living in upscale neighborhood, others in confinement. On the outside they were serving up crocodile delicacies. I declined eating crocodile and got the hell out of there as soon as I could.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;##Bukit bangkirai
Not far away from the zoo, could be found an Oranghutan shelter, working to rescue and rehabilitate these animals have lost their homes as the habitat they once lived in are gone perished. Having met and conversed with their leader in Bukit bangkirai, there was a desire to visit,  but held back by other engagements I didn’t have get an opportunity this time. Their way of running this business came off better than the gig being run in Sarawak, on the Malaysian side.
The canopy in Bukit bangkirai was another disappointment. In large due to their charging a stupendous amount for entry for people with the wrong skin color. It’s not an abnormal thing to be charged more as a foreigner, but it ruins the experience. Many I speak to accept this kind of treatment, but I’m not sure they realize what’s happening to them. The world is full of suckers, it seems. In any case, it didn’t make me feel very welcome.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;From my eyes, the canopy was a sorry attempt to call themselves a tourist attraction. There’s a staircase , walk the canopy and look at the view. A view that was unspectacular and utterly mundane. I didn’t mention the hour long, ardent roads you’ve to put up with too get here. Why the locals bother to come here, will be a mystery. A big tourist trap is what this place.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;So while there may not be many things to do that are worthwhile, one needs to allow for the alternative of meeting up with the local community. More options become available through them… and we ended up having good times, exchanging&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
        
        <pubDate>Thu, 05 Jul 2018 00:00:00 +0700</pubDate>
        <link>
        http://localhost:5000/backpacking-balikpapan-independently</link>
        <guid isPermaLink="true">http://localhost:5000/backpacking-balikpapan-independently</guid>
      </item>
      
    
      
      <item>
        <title>Dayak Festival and Adventure in Tanjung Isuy</title>
        
          <description>&lt;h2 id=&quot;road-trip-to-tanjung-isuy&quot;&gt;Road Trip to Tanjung Isuy&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Word was out, a festival underway, by the Dayaks, drawing me on road trip to the interiors of Kalimantan along with my newfound friends from Samarinda. Name of the village Tanjung isuy, right on Borneo’s biggest lakes and a famed home of the region’s indigenous people, the Dayaks, referring to the native people of Borneo.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Six hours of nonstop motorcycle riding on, by anyone’s standards, horrendous roads, was needed to get there. Potholes designed to kill any vehicle coming in its vicinity, didn’t deter my female travel companions however. Not a bit. They were tougher than nails and more fearless than man. Indeed, they were racing these roads like there wasn’t a tomorrow. In case you’re wondering what crushed glutes feel like, these roads will teach you.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Later, I, of course, learn it’s possible to access these villages using river transport. Perhaps it would have made for a more comfortable experience, but what’s an adventure without discomfort? Besides, bikes gave the flexibility to do our own day trips.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;festival-budaya-in-tanjung-isuy&quot;&gt;Festival Budaya in Tanjung Isuy&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The festival itself attracted many local as well as visitors from neighboring population centers, such as Samarinda. As far as foreigners go, I was the only one there. Unsurprisingly, becoming quite an attraction myself. Indeed, I was informed, my mere presence had added to the festival’s overall glamor and credibility. Me, adding to an event’s success? What a joke. But such becomes the privilege of fair skin and non-black hair in these parts of the world. There is an inexplicable reverence for us.
As for my impressions of the festival, it showcased the cultural elements I’d come for in the first place. Folk costumes, dances, and artwork on display. The onstage performances was a little loud for my liking and could need improvements. Most importantly, to inform these people they need to be more mindful of their ears. Louder is not better. For some reason, the organizers thought louder was cooler. Tinnitus is not cool, however, so I was never able to stay for long.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;exploring-surrounding-villages-tanjung-jan-and-pulau-lanting&quot;&gt;Exploring surrounding villages, Tanjung Jan and Pulau Lanting&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In addition to the festival itself, it’s also possible to explore the surrounding areas. The lake complex is home to multiple villages, most of whom can not be accessed by roads and require some kind of water transport. Not yet having found someone to transport us, we explore the roads on motorbikes, checking out the villages that were connected. It was nice to walk in the surroundings and for the most part, the added attention my skin brings is amusing and tolerable, but after a while it risks becoming exhausting. I get the celebrity experience, without being an actual celibrity.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;tanjung-jone&quot;&gt;Tanjung Jone&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The next day, my resourceful travel companions had succeeded in finding a boat that could take us on the lake to explore the further away villages. A fisherman is willing to take us to Tanjung Jone, a village, as we learn, inhabited by people from the island Sulawesi. An island quite a bit away from here. I’m told they settled down in this remote place about three generations ago and survived by the opportunities granted to them by the river and the lake.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Walking through the village, we come across a woman sitting by her still-to-be erected home. She estimates it will be another 4 years until completion. Her husband earns 50 000 rupiah a day fishing, a little less than $4. The villagers will help in the construction of her home, but material costs will still need to be accounted for. She explains one-hundred-million rupiah, or about $7000, is needed. For now she’s residing in a home that’s about to fall apart.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
        
        <pubDate>Thu, 27 Jul 2017 17:00:00 +0700</pubDate>
        <link>
        http://localhost:5000/adventures-festival-tanjung-isuy</link>
        <guid isPermaLink="true">http://localhost:5000/adventures-festival-tanjung-isuy</guid>
      </item>
      
    
  </channel>
</rss>
